<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Osmos | Arrogant Gamer]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/categories/osmos/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-27T22:23:21+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Arrogant Gamer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Patience and Regret]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/09/29/patience-and-regret/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-29T12:49:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/09/29/patience-and-regret</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are three 'zones', collections of levels each of which give you a different flavor of game play. The
ambient 'vanilla' levels build on the theme of 'become the biggest'. The other two zones change game play
by introducing new elements: artificial lifeforms for you to compete with; and force attractors that act
as a center of gravity. I still haven't figured out how to beat the force attractor levels, but the ambient
and survival levels are great! Beating three ai motes at once is tricky, and took me several tries.</p>

<p>Osmos contains one of my favorite underused mechanics: patience. I can
understand why this mechanic doesn't get a lot of use. In Braid it was
presented only to the most hardcore, and in SS&amp;S EP it was an opt-in
system. In both cases, you didn't have to play the waiting game if you
didn't want to... but in Osmos you better get used to it. In the force
attractor levels you are in orbit around a central goo ball, and you
want to be the biggest. Playing these levels I felt like I had close
to zero agency. "Hey man still in orbit around the force attractor?"
"yeah, how bout you?" "yup. OK well, see you next time around." With
each tearfully slow revolution you might pick up a tiny bit of mass,
and in this manner you grow. Admittedly, Osmos does give you the option
of speeding up time, which I discovered late in the levels by accident
(I don't pay much attention to written instructions); even on fast
forward you still end up spinning in circles for an eternity before
you finally have enough mass to just leave and make a sandwich while
you become the biggest. Great game! But listen, that's not all it takes.</p>

<p>In addition to patience, the game rewards the 'letting go'. I guess it
is a very eastern-religion game in some sense: if you are aiming at
a particular goo ball, and in your clumsy sputtering you manage to
miss the mark, then you had better just let go. You could come to a full
stop and reverse your momentum, or try to come around for a second pass,
but in doing so you lose more than you probably will gain. The best
thing to do when you lose something (like in real life) is to adjust your
plan.</p>

<p>Patience: become the biggest, and never look back.</p>

<p>of which introduces a new element: opponents that behave
in one way or another; force attractors around which all the motes orbit;</p>

<p>The next few give us toy examples of the game's 'zones', each of which tests us by introducing new elements.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Become the Biggest]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/09/22/osmos/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-22T18:28:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/09/22/osmos</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You could play Osmos with no more instruction: the imperative to grow will guide you naturally
and inexorably. Despite its simplicity, Osmos does insist on spelling everything out in tutorial levels. I
really enjoy early learning stages in games, especially the ones that teach you about the world, rather than
the control scheme. I'm usually not pleased when English language words appear on the screen telling me
to tap X rapidly or whatnot. Unless the appearance of language is consistent with the theme of the game,
(like in Analogue, for example) this can be a real turn off. I'm going to go into some detail about the tutorial
levels (there are two) because I think Osmos is an excellent example of how easily a great beginning can
turn foul.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Starting a game with a quote by a physicist or philosopher is a great idea: it sets the stage, and fills my mind
with well grounded ideas. No better way to quickly build a framework in which a player's understanding
of the theme and action can grow, than by analogy. Osmos begins with a quote by Newton that has acquired
great cultural weight, and has as much meaning in ethics as it does in physics. Great first moment.</p>

<p>Then, fade in to a beautiful blue orb, pulsing and swimming with activity. What is this? Is this the universe? Is this
life itself, or God? No, the game corrects us: "This is you". Beautiful! OK! Now I know what kind of game
this is and who I am, just give me a goal and I'm off!</p>

<p><img class="left-side" src="/images/this-is-you.png"></p>

<p>Aiming for the home run, Osmos zooms out, and shows us what we need to do: "Propel yourself to the blue
circle and come to a stop". For me, a smooth introduction like this is the sweetest thing. I rarely
play games to their conclusion, and I judge very quickly. Ambient music, soft blue colour-scheme, and
simple direct instructions are exactly everything that I need. So, having been told what I am and
where to go, naturally I start clicking.</p>

<p>Nothing... click, click, click! Wait what? But I thought every action had an equal and opposite reaction?
Shouldn't something happen when I click? Oh wait... I see what's up. Osmos doesn't care if I understand what
I am and where I should go: it is too humble (or something) to anticipate that I could have understood by now
just based on the theme and visuals. So, reluctantly, I press the spacebar one more time.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>"Hey, listen! You navigate by aligning the cursor behind you and pressing the left mouse button"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Arglebargle!!! I love Osmos: great game. I'm just so, so, so disappointed when that little sprite
shows up in every game I play to remind me of what I already know. I've never read a novel or watched a
film that presumed the need to explain the medium: yet every second video game does this. Especially
considering that Osmos was released for a platform with exactly one button -- your finger -- which can only
be used to 'tip-tap'... it is very sad that I'm not allowed to play until that vile spectre has made my
means of agency explicit.</p>

<p>The rest of the instructions -- that is, to absorb small motes and avoid big ones -- are also unnecessary
in the post katamari damaci world. Especially when the reds of warning are so vivid, and the peaceful blues
so soft and attractive. Nothing in the world could be more evident, once you have understood that 'this is you'. If
that's me, and that big red ball isn't me, then there is no way I'm going anywhere near it. I'll go chill
with these little blue balls I can shove around. Oh shit I got bigger! Ha, and the red ball changed color! Time
to win!</p>

<p>See: no need to instruct. Hey! Are you listening?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
