<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: non-sighted play | Arrogant Gamer]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/categories/non-sighted-play/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-02T22:02:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Arrogant Gamer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Echo Beasts]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/07/06/echo-beasts/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-06T17:13:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/07/06/echo-beasts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently became excited about the prospect of games for non-sighted people. This came after playing a couple of LD26 games that involved
elements of non-sighted play. These were <a href="http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-26/?action=preview&amp;uid=1158">Conversion</a>, and <a href="http://rac7.com/YouMustEscape/">You Must Escape</a>, and they succeed in being about accessibility without being accessible.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="center" src="/images/you-must-escape.png" title="&#34;You Must Escape&#34;" alt="&#34;You Must Escape&#34;"></p>

<p><a href="http://rac7.com/YouMustEscape/">You Must Escape</a> was one of my favorite games of the LD26 (it was one of everyone's favorites). It was moody, minimal, fun to control, and punishingly hard. The
game models navigation by echo-location, representing sound as point particles that emanate out from the source of the sound. This is really compelling!
Just moving around in the environment creates footsteps that are essentially explosions of little white particles, which bounce off the contours of the rooms
and hallways, giving you a sense of their shape. You can also press the spacebar to make an intentional sound, which is louder the longer you hold the spacebar, or
hold shift to creep, producing no sound. In addition to topography, you also get a sense of the 'texture' of rooms, because the particles change colour depending
on the texture of the reflective surface. The textures presented in the game world are: grey for nothing, red for danger, and white for goal.</p>

<p>This by itself would be a fun game, but You Must Escape takes it further by introducing horrifying echo beasts: a source of sound that produces red particles, and
registers as danger. These creatures are mobile, and track toward the source of a sound. The later levels are extremely difficult, as you must often stay completely
still or navigate blindly by "creeping" around the level. In any case, the sound effects generated by echo beasts in motion are horrible alien noises, and the hero's
death-rattle is so awful that I found myself dreading death (actually, I gave up in the end: this game is too scary for me).</p>

<p>Reading the comments to You Must Escape was neat: so many comments, but no-one commented on the inherent irony of the game. One comment in particular stood out
for me:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>"I'm so bad at these blind sound-dependent games. I wish I was better at them. Good job."</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Since You Must Escape is not a sound-dependent game at all, I take "These blind sound-dependent games" to refer to games like <a href="http://rac7.com/YouMustEscape/">Conversion</a>, You Must Escape, and Traal
(in the most extreme case) in which elements of non-sighted play take the fore. They force the gamer to create a model of their environment in a way they might not be
used to, and I think this is a good thing. These elements are introduced in different levels of purity, or perhaps abstraction: in Conversion the game comes closest to
being an actual non-sighted experience; in You Must Escape the game models a non-sighted experience; and in Traal, where the player must close their eyes from time to
time in order to advance, we are just given a taste of non-sighted play.</p>

<p>Game designers are always systematizing elements of experience. Whether this is a physics engine, or a haunted forest, the designer chooses ways to evoke a particular
feeling in their players. I feel like You Must Escape does an excellent job of being a fun game about echolocation, but not such a great job of evoking the feeling of
echolocating.</p>

<p>has to choose
When I play a game like You Must Escape, which models something. , I always wonder about the choice of paint. For example: in an RPG amnesia is modeled by dropping a player
into an unfamiliar situation.
elements This phenomenon is one of degrees: in the case of Conversion, as I've mentioned, I am sad that the game remained inaccessible. This game, however, does not
present a non-sighted experience; it models one. The Why use point particles
to represent sound waves when sound waves would do a much better job?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.blindsidegame.com/">blindside</a>
<a href="http://www.papasangre.com/">papasangre</a>
<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zeBFCQ-aBds">nightjar</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elements of non-sighted play]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/06/25/elements-of-non-sighted-play/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-25T21:53:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/06/25/elements-of-non-sighted-play</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently became excited about the prospect of games for non-sighted people. This came after playing a couple of LD26 games that involved
elements of non-sighted play. These were <a href="http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-26/?action=preview&amp;uid=1158">Conversion</a>, and <a href="http://rac7.com/YouMustEscape/">You Must Escape</a>, and they succeed in being about accessibility without being accessible.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="center" src="/images/conversion.png" title="&#34;Conversion&#34;" alt="&#34;Conversion&#34;"></p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='you should really
skip this bit and just play the damn game, that would be easier'>
<a href="http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-26/?action=preview&amp;uid=1158">Conversion</a> is a 1st (or possibly 3rd) person shooter that relies on none of the visual cues FPS players have been trained to use. The screen is black at all times,
except when messages concerning the state of the environment are displayed, these being "you bumped into a wall!" or "there is something soft and wet at your feet".
The rest of the game information is conveyed with audio cues, such as a dripping noise, your own heartbeat, or a gunshot. These effects are presented using positional audio,
so that the player wearing headphones can effectively navigate to the source of a sound by positioning it directly in front of them and moving forward (you should really
skip this bit and just play the damn game, that would be easier).</p>

<p>Audio cues used in the game are gritty and emotional: water dripping in an empty room, a scratching noise, and a heartbeat are all very visceral. When I heard the gunshot
noise for the first time I literally leapt from my chair. After that I kept my tongue tucked behind my teeth in anticipation of more punishing audio to come. Conversion is
an excellent and effective game, and it was well received during LD26.
</span></p>

<p>The game introduces a sighted audience to elements of the world perceived by non-sighted people; its title is a reference to a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conversion_disorder"> kind of neurological disorder </a> that
can cause blindness.  That having been said, Conversion is not playable by non-sighted
gamers, and this feels like an ironic and tragic oversight. Despite <a href="https://twitter.com/spiridios">@spiridios</a>' claim that "You cannot see, so you must complete the game using only your sense of hearing
and sense of touch", Conversion actually relies on the gamer's sense of sight as well since it conveys certain spatial information in written messages. I want my review
to remain positive, because Conversion really is a great game, but I also can't shy away from what I see as a glaring and embarrassing truth: a sighted gamer made a game
about being blind, without considering whether blind people would be able to play it too.</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='it is not interesting as a proof of concept'>
Conversion really does shine as an innovative indie title, but it is not interesting as a proof of concept. There are already fully 3D first-person-shooters made by and for non-sighted gamers. If you sit down and give them a
whirl as a sighted player... all I can say is that you will be stunned. Games like <a href="http://www.gmagames.com/sod.html"> Shades of Doom </a> and <a href="http://www.kaldobsky.com/audiogames/"> Swamp </a> are engineered to be complete, accessible FPS
experiences -- an indie made for a game jam just can't compete. I took some time to play SOD as part of writing this post: it was extremely
challenging for me to make any headway at all, but by all accounts this game broke ground. I haven't tried Swamp, but <a href="http://soundplay.pitchfork.com/articles/shining-in-the-darkness/">Jason Johnson</a>'s review got me pretty excited. These
are the proof of concept games that could be considered landmarks in some way. Conversion is not them.
</span></p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='it was made to be experienced'>
Conversion is something that those games aren't. I found the soundscape of Shades of Doom crowded and obnoxious. It was easy to navigate, with lots more
beeps and audio cues, but it wasn't beautiful. SOD and Swamp are games that were made to be played.
Conversion, on the other hand, was tight and personal; it was made to be experienced. In particular it was made to be exprienced by a group of sighted gamers,
and to them it really was unique and new. This is well and good, but consider what was lost: Conversion could have been such
a perfect experience to share with non-sighted gamers, if only it didn't rely on sight.
</span></p>

<p>There is a nice bridge to be built here, and the cost of construction is extremely low.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
