<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: non-sighted play | Arrogant Gamer]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/categories/non-sighted-play/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-22T00:11:02-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Arrogant Gamer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Echo Beasts]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2014/04/21/echo-beasts/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-21T16:13:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2014/04/21/echo-beasts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while back, I became excited about the prospect of games for non-sighted people. This came after playing a couple of LD26 games that involved
elements of non-sighted play. I wrote about <a href="http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-26/?action=preview&amp;uid=1158">Conversion</a> in a <a href="/blog/2013/06/25/elements-of-non-sighted-play/">previous post</a>, but <a href="http://rac7.com/YouMustEscape/">You Must Escape</a> is just as interesting.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="center" src="/images/you-must-escape.png" title="&ldquo;You Must Escape&rdquo;" ></p>

<p><a href="http://rac7.com/YouMustEscape/">You Must Escape</a> was one of my favorite games of the LD26 (it was one of everyone&rsquo;s favorites). It was moody, minimal, fun to control, and punishingly hard. The
game models navigation by echo-location, representing sound as point particles that emanate out from the source of the sound. This is really compelling!
Just moving around in the environment creates footsteps that are essentially explosions of little white particles, which bounce off the contours of the rooms
and hallways, giving you a sense of their shape. You can also press the spacebar to make an intentional sound, which is louder the longer you hold the spacebar, or
hold shift to creep, producing no sound. In addition to topography, you also get a sense of the &lsquo;texture&rsquo; of rooms, because the particles change colour depending
on the texture of the reflective surface. The textures presented in the game world are: grey for nothing, red for danger, and white for goal.</p>

<p>This by itself would be a fun game, but You Must Escape takes it further by introducing horrifying echo beasts: a source of sound that produces red particles, and
registers as danger. These creatures are mobile, and track toward the source of a sound. The later levels are extremely difficult, as you must often stay completely
still or navigate blindly by &ldquo;creeping&rdquo; around the level. In any case, the sound effects generated by echo beasts in motion are horrible alien noises, and the hero&rsquo;s
death-rattle is so awful that I found myself dreading death (actually, I gave up in the end: this game is too scary for me).</p>

<p>Reading the comments to You Must Escape was neat. One comment in particular stood out for me:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>&ldquo;I&rsquo;m so bad at these blind sound-dependent games. I wish I was better at them. Good job.&rdquo;</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Since You Must Escape is not a sound-dependent game at all, I take &ldquo;these blind sound-dependent games&rdquo; to refer to games like <a href="http://rac7.com/YouMustEscape/">Conversion</a>, You Must Escape, and <a href="http://www.draknek.org/games/traal/">Traal</a>,
in which elements of non-sighted play take the fore. They force the gamer to create a model of their environment in a way they might not be
used to, and I think this is a good thing. These elements are introduced in different levels of purity, or perhaps abstraction: in Conversion the game comes closest to
being an actual non-sighted experience; in You Must Escape the game models a non-sighted experience; and in Traal, where the player must close their eyes from time to
time in order to advance, we are just given a taste of non-sighted play.</p>

<p>Game designers are always systematizing elements of experience. Whether this is a physics engine, or a haunted forest, the designer chooses ways to evoke a particular
feeling in their players. I feel like You Must Escape does an excellent job of being a fun game about echolocation, but not such a great job of evoking the feeling of
actually echolocating. It isn&rsquo;t so much a &ldquo;blind sound-dependent&rdquo; game; rather it is about blindness and sound-dependence. If you are interested in trying your hand
at some games that actually <em>are</em> &ldquo;blind sound-dependent games&rdquo;, I recommend checking out <a href="http://www.blindsidegame.com/">blindside</a>, <a href="http://www.papasangre.com/">papasangre</a>, or <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zeBFCQ-aBds">nightjar</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elements of non-sighted play]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/06/25/elements-of-non-sighted-play/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-25T21:53:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/06/25/elements-of-non-sighted-play</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently became excited about the prospect of games for non-sighted people. This came after playing a couple of LD26 games that involved
elements of non-sighted play. These were <a href="http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-26/?action=preview&amp;uid=1158">Conversion</a>, and <a href="http://rac7.com/YouMustEscape/">You Must Escape</a>, and they succeed in being about accessibility without being accessible.</p>

<p>I wrote about You Must Escape as <a href="/blog/2013/07/06/echo-beasts/">a separate post</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="center" src="/images/conversion.png" title="&ldquo;Conversion&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<p>The game introduces a sighted audience to elements of the world perceived by non-sighted people; its title is a reference to a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conversion_disorder">kind of neurological disorder</a> that
can cause blindness.  That having been said, Conversion is not playable by non-sighted
gamers, and this feels like an ironic and tragic oversight. Despite <a href="https://twitter.com/spiridios">@spiridios</a>&lsquo; claim that &ldquo;You cannot see, so you must complete the game using only your sense of hearing
and sense of touch&rdquo;, Conversion actually relies on the gamer&rsquo;s sense of sight as well since it conveys certain spatial information in written messages. I want my review
to remain positive, because Conversion really is a great game, but I also can&rsquo;t shy away from what I see as a glaring and embarrassing truth: a sighted gamer made a game
about being blind, without considering whether blind people would be able to play it too.</p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<p>There is a nice bridge to be built here, and the cost of construction is extremely low.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
