<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Mirror's Edge | Arrogant Gamer]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/categories/mirror-s-edge/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-27T22:23:21+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Arrogant Gamer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meat's Edge]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/07/26/meats-edge/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-26T16:20:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/07/26/meats-edge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Meat's Edge is a first person take on the unforgiving twitch platformer,
that doesn't shy away from nausea and vomit. Missing a jump generally means
being torn into pink strips and recycled, rather than shimmying up a red pipe.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Meat's Edge takes human reflexes to the extreme. It takes all the vomit
inducing vertigo of <a href="http://www.penny-arcade.com/comic/2008/11/03"> Mirror's Edge </a> and just runs with it: camera angles are
spinning and flailing as your body rag-dolls madly after a failed landing.
More rolling, more cart-wheels, and more acrobatics. You spend the game
sprinting across rooftops, but unlike in Mirror's Edge the rooftops of this
<a href="http://aliendovecote.com/uploads/twine/tycoon/crime.html">post neo-capitalist global empire</a> are designed to deter runners with the same
vicious geometry that modern architecture leverages against pigeons and the
homeless. I'm talking about spikes. This is is not a world that was designed
by the naive: they know what you are and what you do, and everything up here
is intended to stop you.</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='Everything about Meat&#8217;s Edge is designed to remind you what you&#8217;re made of.'>
In Mirror's Edge the first person perspective was <a href="http://www.wired.com/gaming/gamingreviews/commentary/games/2008/11/gamesfrontiers_1117">emphasized</a> by including
heavy breathing, gasps, and your ever-present arms and legs. Meat's Edge
takes this further: the phantom of your nose and upper lip is always
there; strands of your thick black hair fall into your face as the wind
crashing between the skyscrapers whips them to life; stand still for a moment
(not recommended) and you will notice tiny fibers <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Floater">floating around inside your eye</a>.
The environment is just as cruel as your anatomy: torrential
rain, tear gas, or smoke belched from the factories gets in your eyes, blurs
your vision, and reduces your chances of making that next jump; bright flashes
of light stay with you, discolouring your surroundings. Ice level? Yeah, Meat's
Edge has <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/SlippySlideyIceWorld">an ice level</a>. Everything about Meat's Edge is designed to remind you what you're made of.
</span></p>

<p><span class='pullquote-left' data-pullquote='This is not a game that
EA would ever publish.'>
The level layouts are brutal! There are no brightly painted red pipes to shimmy up
in this game; there are no long runs through corridors. Meat's Edge borrows
its level design from twitch platformers like <a href="http://supermeatboy.com/">Super Meat Boy</a>, and its pace (and
respect for your feelings) from <a href="http://superhexagon.com/"> Super Hexagon </a>. There are no arena zones filled with rifle toting corporate
military, and if you do happen to cross paths with an armed guard, renegade
cyborg, or corporate ninja charged with recovering the sensitive info you
are running... <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RwtifqCmGuw"> you do what we do </a>. Conflicts fought among the scaffolds and
reflective plexiglass tend to be short and conclusive. This is not a game that
EA would ever publish.</p>

<p>Oh, and the dude on your intercom? Calling you names the whole fucking way.
</span></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
