<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Vision by Proxy | Arrogant Gamer]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/categories/vision-by-proxy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-22T00:09:23-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Arrogant Gamer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vision by Proxy]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/04/06/vision-by-proxy/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-06T21:49:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/04/06/vision-by-proxy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In Vision by Proxy, you are a nearly blind extraterrestrial who sees by
stealing human eyes. When you steal a pair of eyes, looking out through them
gives you a different perspective on the world. A child&rsquo;s world is full
of magic, while an engineer sees the hidden uses of things. To progress
through the game, you must collect eyes.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="left-side" src="/images/vision-by-proxy.png"></p>

<p>Your alien character does not power up by collecting eyes. Instead you gradually
gain access to different interpretations of the level&rsquo;s layout. Thus, ideally,
the game is about remembering that you can more easily climb the little girl&rsquo;s
play-fort then the anime chick&rsquo;s Japanese temple. Some perspectives give you access
to the insides of things, or to a variety of floating platforms.</p>

<p>This game has evolved quite a bit since its initial incarnation, and some of my
original complaints have been addressed. In <a href="http://www.kongregate.com/games/rosyPenguin/vision-by-proxy-2nd-ed">&ldquo;Vision by Proxy: Second Edition&rdquo;</a>,
there were only four eyes to collect, but in the more recent iteration
(<a href="http://www.kongregate.com/games/Giraffasaurus/ms-vision-by-proxy">&ldquo;Ms Vision by Proxy&rdquo;</a>) we are introduced to seven or so. This is great! When
we enter a level we aren&rsquo;t certain what eyes will be available, and only after
developing a vocabulary of game objects we can begin to predict what eyes we need
in order to progress.</p>

<p>That being said, it still suffers from the levels being too big for the hero: the gameplay
is a little like a metroidvania, but the RPG elements are not played up enough for trekking back and forth across
the level to really be exciting. In addition, the puzzles are not really difficult or
focused and solving them ends up feeling inevitable. This game needs an overworld map, or teleportation, or something
to make the player feel like they are gathering information towards eventually solving
the puzzle, rather than just walking back and forth.</p>

<p>I think I&rsquo;d like to play a similar game in which there is no central &ldquo;main character&rdquo;.
Rather than having the one character collect all the other perspectives, the player
could switch between the perspectives, essentially teleporting around the level. This
way the player could get an overall sense of the layout without actually having to
trudge around it. Each available character would be trapped in some way by terrain
that they can&rsquo;t perceive their way around. In order to advance, the player would need
to gradually &ldquo;combine&rdquo; the available characters, allowing them to explore larger areas.
Maybe the characters are robots with different sensors that can literally combine to
share information. Maybe the characters don&rsquo;t occupy the same time/space, and each other
character appears as a ghost to the rest, haunting a particular location. Communicating
across this ethereal barrier could provide a mechanism for combining perspectives.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
