<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ludum Dare | Arrogant Gamer]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/categories/ludum-dare/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-20T23:27:31-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Arrogant Gamer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elements of non-sighted play]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/06/25/elements-of-non-sighted-play/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-25T21:53:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/06/25/elements-of-non-sighted-play</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently became excited about the prospect of games for non-sighted people. This came after playing a couple of LD26 games that involved
elements of non-sighted play. These were <a href="http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-26/?action=preview&amp;uid=1158">Conversion</a>, and <a href="http://rac7.com/YouMustEscape/">You Must Escape</a>, and they succeed in being about accessibility without being accessible.</p>

<p>I wrote about You Must Escape as <a href="/blog/2013/07/06/echo-beasts/">a separate post</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="center" src="/images/conversion.png" title="&ldquo;Conversion&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<p>The game introduces a sighted audience to elements of the world perceived by non-sighted people; its title is a reference to a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conversion_disorder">kind of neurological disorder</a> that
can cause blindness.  That having been said, Conversion is not playable by non-sighted
gamers, and this feels like an ironic and tragic oversight. Despite <a href="https://twitter.com/spiridios">@spiridios</a>&lsquo; claim that &ldquo;You cannot see, so you must complete the game using only your sense of hearing
and sense of touch&rdquo;, Conversion actually relies on the gamer&rsquo;s sense of sight as well since it conveys certain spatial information in written messages. I want my review
to remain positive, because Conversion really is a great game, but I also can&rsquo;t shy away from what I see as a glaring and embarrassing truth: a sighted gamer made a game
about being blind, without considering whether blind people would be able to play it too.</p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<p>There is a nice bridge to be built here, and the cost of construction is extremely low.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Two LD26 Entries]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/05/20/two-ld26-entries/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-20T18:09:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/05/20/two-ld26-entries</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-26/?action=preview&amp;uid=5275">DOE</a> and <a href="http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-26/?action=preview&amp;uid=2297">Bashland</a> are two LD26 games feel amazingly polished given that they were made in 48 hours. Bashland describes itself as a &ldquo;Breakout Mario Mashup&rdquo;, and does an incredible job of being just that. DOE takes place in a detailed and nuanced world, in which dreams can touch reality.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>DOE</h3>

<p><img class="left-side" src="/images/we-can-all-dream.png" title="&ldquo;we can all dream&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>One of the clever decisions in DOE is to have the game set in a detailed and nuanced world, without ever really referencing that world. In the author&rsquo;s own words, &ldquo;The whole universe that I imagined is in the end much bigger than what is exposed in the game.&rdquo; DOE&rsquo;s gameplay is familiar &mdash; it is a mixture of pushing blocks and avoiding guards &mdash; but the visual elements, events, and ending give us a sense that we are experiencing the exposed edge of something bigger.</p>

<p>In the early areas you explore by pushing walls away, presumably with your mind, though there is also evidence to suggest that your mind powers are being suppressed somehow (thus, we may suspect that someone is helping you escape). Early on we get some clues by way of overheard conversation, or intrapersonal communication:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>&ldquo;Let them imagine you&rsquo;re dead, and you will be.&rdquo;</p></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>&ldquo;This is going to be tricky&hellip; and I can&rsquo;t dream!&rdquo;</p></blockquote></p>

<p>When the game ends, all I want it more. How do you make a game like this in 48 hours?</p>

<h3>Bashland</h3>

<p>Bashland, on the other hand, is not a subtly, nuanced or carefully constructed poem fit tightly in a 48 hour shell; it is a full blown explosion where nostalgia slams up against honestly amazing assets. When I started it, I had to double check that I was not, in fact, playing a jam game. The music, graphics, and gameplay are completely stunning and 100% communicate the subject. The music! It is just baddass.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/bashland.png" title="&ldquo;A Breakout Mario Mashup&rdquo;" ></p>

<p><blockquote><p>BASHLAND. When you played breakout, this is what you imagined you were playing. Nice slow reveal. @McFunkypants <a href="http://t.co/Cetc19ApVW">http://t.co/Cetc19ApVW</a> #LD48</p><footer><strong>@ArrogantGamer</strong> <cite>A Truly Arrogant Man</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>When I tweeted this, I actually hadn&rsquo;t read the author&rsquo;s statement quoted above. The game feels like Breakout literally breaking out of the restrictive old-school arcade genre &mdash; it&rsquo;s as though the little ball finally bashed through its enclosure and into someone else&rsquo;s game. Gradually, we realize this is exactly what happened. It is so satisfying to bash your way through the old Mario stages, and the control is also really nice and smooth. Finally, if you manage to bash away too much of the level you can no longer win: so practice some restraint!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minimalism: Pyramid]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/05/15/minimalism-pyramid/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-15T23:37:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/05/15/minimalism-pyramid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Many LD26 games chose to incorporate the theme of Minimalism by being visually simple. Pyramid was visually simple as a consequence of being minimalist. Burgess chose to strip away the unnecessary elements of a rogue-like, and left us with a stunning piece of work. I will dwell on the degree to which Burgess hit the theme.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="left-side" src="/images/pyramid.png"></p>

<p>Minimalism presents something similar to prototype. I think that word has a bit of baggage: evoking an incomplete or fragile &lsquo;first try&rsquo; that is a basis for greater efforts. Prototypes aren&rsquo;t just a quick slap job, they must also be the minimal viable product. That&rsquo;s why projects start as prototypes, but it is not to say that we can&rsquo;t also start with something bigger and then shave it down to a prototype. This is how I understood the LD26 theme, and I think that Burgess really expressed it well in Pyramid.</p>

<p><img class="left-side" src="/images/hooked-lash.png">
<img class="right-side" src="/images/one-of-the-corrupted.png"></p>

<p>Pyramid&rsquo;s levels are squares of randomly generated passages; the hero&rsquo;s vision is limited, so when the levels start to get really big it starts to feel really murky. If Pyramid&rsquo;s levels didn&rsquo;t grow, we wouldn&rsquo;t understand the name. If Pyramid were called another name, we wouldn&rsquo;t understand why the levels grow. Remove either element and what remains doesn&rsquo;t make sense. Very little is embellished in Pyramid; there is very little excess. That&rsquo;s not to say there isn&rsquo;t anything left that could still be stripped away: burgess named things. Numbers appear on the screen to indicate the damage the hero deals or takes: this is enough to express the gradual powering up of the hero. Burgess, however, chose to name the different power levels. For example, in Pyramid &ldquo;10&rdquo; is called &ldquo;Imperious Axe of Truth&rdquo;. The monsters are also named.</p>

<p>In terms of how the game plays: it is smooth and fun. The game teaches us all the necessary mechanics in the first 3 levels, and then just gets tougher and tougher. The only thing that is left to us to discover is how combat works. I found out around level 12 that if you touch an enemy you attack it. That&rsquo;s not all though: unlike a run-of-the-mill rogue-like, it is possible to dance with enemies and outwit them. For me this is great: the game is not just a resource management slog, it involves patience and wit as well.</p>

<p>The game goes on forever, but I&rsquo;ve been assured that level 48 is the last time any new content is introduced.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Death Death Evolution]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/10/01/death-death-evolution/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-01T19:35:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/10/01/death-death-evolution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In Death Death Evolution, there is no escape. You must die to advance.
This game proposes a new relationship between the platform
jumper and the pits. In later stages I was actively looking for places
where I could die in a particular way, in order to unlock the tools I
might need later. There are even levels where you can die in irrelevant
ways, if you choose to, so that if you want to you can be stingy with death,
or feed her to bursting in order to fully &lsquo;power up&rsquo;.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="right-side" src="/images/dde.png"></p>

<p>Nice game: I want more. More different animals, evolution abilities that
make more sense (I mean&hellip; I fell on spikes and could subsequently break
balloons with my head). I think we could take the mechanic of dying
for personal gain, switch up the theme a bit, and make a truly golden game
about ghosts or reincarnation or something.</p>

<p>I guess that&rsquo;s what LD24 was all about.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
