<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://yoursite.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://yoursite.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-09-27T19:36:30-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://yoursite.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Become the Biggest]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/blog/2012/09/22/osmos/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-22T18:28:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/blog/2012/09/22/osmos</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Notes: small game, just deserves a small review. Touch on features that are good in games, like how
self explanatory it is. Relate it to another game?</p>

<p>You could almost play Osmos with no more instruction: this maxim and a few clicks of the mouse are more than enough.
Osmos does insist on spelling things out for us: the first few levels teach us explicitly how to maneuver in the
world. I can forgive this though, maybe because it is a fairly abstract game with no pressing need to establish
suspension of disbelief.</p>

<p>There are three &#8216;zones&#8217;, collections of levels each of which give you a different flavor of game play. The
ambient &#8216;vanilla&#8217; levels build on the theme of &#8216;become the biggest&#8217;. The other two zones change game play
by introducing new elements: artificial lifeforms for you to compete with; and force attractors that act
as a center of gravity. I still haven&#8217;t figured out how to beat the force attractor levels, but the ambient
and survival levels are great! Beating three ai motes at once is tricky, and took me several tries.</p>

<p>Osmos contains one of my favorite underused mechanics: patience. I can
understand why this mechanic doesn&#8217;t get a lot of use. In Braid it was
presented only to the most hardcore, and in SS&amp;S EP it was an opt-in
system. In both cases, you didn&#8217;t have to play the waiting game if you
didn&#8217;t want to&#8230; but in Osmos you better get used to it. In the force
attractor levels you are in orbit around a central goo ball, and you
want to be the biggest. Playing these levels I felt like I had close
to zero agency. &#8220;Hey man still in orbit around the force attractor?&#8221;
&#8220;yeah, how bout you?&#8221; &#8220;yup. OK well, see you next time around.&#8221; With
each tearfully slow revolution you might pick up a tiny bit of mass,
and in this manner you grow. Admittedly, Osmos does give you the option
of speeding up time, which I discovered late in the levels by accident
(I don&#8217;t pay much attention to written instructions); even on fast
forward you still end up spinning in circles for an eternity before
you finally have enough mass to just leave and make a sandwich while
you become the biggest. Great game! But listen, that&#8217;s not all it takes.</p>

<p>In addition to patience, the game rewards the &#8216;letting go&#8217;. I guess it
is a very eastern-religion game in some sense: if you are aiming at
a particular goo ball, and in your clumsy sputtering you manage to
miss the mark, then you had better just let go. You could come to a full
stop and reverse your momentum, or try to come around for a second pass,
but in doing so you lose more than you probably will gain. The best
thing to do when you lose something (like in real life) is to adjust your
plan.</p>

<p>Patience: become the biggest, and never look back.</p>

<p>of which introduces a new element: opponents that behave
in one way or another; force attractors around which all the motes orbit;</p>

<p>The next few give us toy examples of the game&#8217;s &#8216;zones&#8217;, each of which tests us by introducing new elements.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Post]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/blog/2012/09/17/first-post/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-17T18:58:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/blog/2012/09/17/first-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Whoa!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
