<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Arrogant Gamer]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-02T22:11:59+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Arrogant Gamer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Portal 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/09/14/portal-2/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-14T21:32:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/09/14/portal-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Congruence]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/09/14/congruence/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-14T19:44:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/09/14/congruence</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My first instinct was to ignore <a href="http://contrastgame.com/">Contrast</a>. I passed it by many times in the <a href="http://indiemegabooth.com/">indie megabooth</a> because it didn&#8217;t inspire me. If I wanted a new
portalesque I would prefer <a href="http://www.steveswink.com/scale/">Scale</a> or <a href="http://www.againstthewallgame.com/">Against the Wall</a>. When, finally, I stopped and watched the trailer&#8230; I cried! Not a teary fellow,
in general, but this game pulled my heart guts in a new way. At this point it was inevitable that I play it, and once I was playing it I new this was
the one.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Contrast is a new entry in the burgeoning subgenre spawned by <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4drucg1A6Xk">Portal</a>. It
presents a (somewhat) unique mechanic, spends the entire game exploring
it, and apparently <em>almost</em> avoids combat. This is great! When I finished
Portal, all I wanted was more Portal (and <a href="https://twitter.com/ArrogantGamer/status/378982421934260224">Portal 2</a> just really didn&#8217;t cut it). It seems I wasn&#8217;t alone.
In Contrast you can walk on shadows. As the game&#8217;s main character, Dawn, you must navigate a 3D world where you push and
pull objects relative to light sources, so as to create a platformable 2D world. Then, you platform along to the next
narrative node. Fits the pattern, but also sounds a lot like <a href="http://www.seewithperspective.com/">Perspective</a>
(or the earlier <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xbuXx6vXeZ8">Lost in Shadow</a>). Some tropes that portalesques have displayed so far (such as waking up
in a mysterious facility) are missing here, and so it is tempting to just think of Contrast as an action platformer. <a href="http://www.1up.com/news/contrast-puzzle-game-about-shadows">An interview with the creator</a>, however, puts this question to rest.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/images/dawn-and-didi.jpg" title="&#34;Dawn and Didi&#34;" alt="&#34;Dawn and Didi&#34;"></p>

<p>Very little storytelling is ever done with a game&#8217;s core mechanic. Am I wrong? Basically it seems to me that in Mario you jump, but
jumping itself is never used to deliver plot. Jumping doesn&#8217;t tell us anything about Mario. Similarly, portals tell us very
little about Chell (more on that later) and in general it is quite rare for the core activity of a game to really relate
to the narrative, except in that it carries us from one narrative node to the next. Gameplay is usually the &#8220;fun part&#8221; that strings together the narrative; or it is the thing that we have to do in order to continue to enjoy the
narrative, depending on who you ask. But when was the last time you played a game in which the core mechanic was the narrative (or vis-versa)?
What would that even look like?</p>

<p>Well here&#8217;s an example: in Portal you never encounter a mirror or any exposition that tells you who you are. You never find a big obvious
shrine with a painting of your character. <a href="http://www.thinkwithportals.com/comic/">Never</a>. Instead the avatar is only introduced by and through
the core gameplay mechanism. You think with portals, and you reflect with portals too. Early on, and whenever you please, you can look
at Chell through the portals and come to feel a little closer to your character. The rest of the time, in Portal as in most games,
puzzle time and story time are separated both in terms of where and when they occur, and in terms of the media of content delivery. Another good
example is <a href="http://fuckyeahdanhibiki.tumblr.com/">Dan</a> in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Street_Fighter_(video_game)">Street Fighter</a>: he is a painting of a character; the paint is game mechanics.</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='Didi really gives the impression of being your younger sibling'>
In the Contrast demo I never felt like I was shadow walking my way from one narrative node to the
next, even though Contrast is exactly the sort of game that could feel that way. The narrative was
skillfully delivered by the shadow mechanic: in the theater area are you are arranging shadows both to
platform on and also to give those shadows a voice. This is seamless! More importantly, though (and this has something to do with why I cried at the trailer),
the younger sister Didi&#8217;s constant chatter never left me a moment
to really feel like I was just moving to the next point in the narrative. We are always playing together! Hers is not a
driving narrative voice justifying your every action, or giving you quests over an intercom; and it isn&#8217;t <a href="http://www.vgcats.com/comics/?strip_id=42">navi</a> with her constant barking, either. It is something
I really haven&#8217;t seen before. Didi really gives the impression of being your younger sibling. She
makes recommendations, but they are delivered in such a way that it always sounds like something she wants to <em>see</em> you do, rather than something she
thinks you <em>should</em> do. If you&#8217;ve ever spent an afternoon running around with a five
year old, you will agree that they love to play the leader. Unlike adults, though, what they want from leadership is not status or productivity: they want you
to model for them.
They want to see how amazing you &#8211; the giant larger-than-life adult &#8211; can be. The task at hand is less important to them than its skillful execution by their
role model. And so it is with Didi. She is always excited to see more, and this manages to create a heart-felt
and caring relationship &#8211; even in the span of a 10 minute demo. In addition, her little sound-bytes, while environmental, don&#8217;t feel like they
are keyed directly to simple events like entering or leaving a room, or completing a puzzle as they might have been in a lesser game. They are crafted in such a way
that she just seems
honestly thrilled that you are spending the night running around with her. Not only is the relationship between the sisters an ever-present part of the soundscape, it is also part of the landscape. This is really how the game got
me to throw up my arms in delight: Didi&#8217;s shadow is often a platform. While you are
leaping between the shadows of horses in the carousel area, Didi&#8217;s shadow is riding one of the horses. &#8220;Oops, sorry!&#8221; she declares as
she ducks out of the way, as if she wasn&#8217;t thrilled out of her mind watching you leap over her shadow.
</span></p>

<p>I got pretty emotional during <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b2AOO89UjSM">Didi&#8217;s trailer</a> when the characters are shown watching fireworks together; when I realized that this
was a game in which a little girl and her female role model could watch
fireworks on a balcony, without needing to dote on the attentions of the male leads. I was already sold, playing the demo convinced
me that not only was this that game, but it was also a skillfully told story. It was scenes like Didi raising a stick so that you can cross its
enormous shadow that impressed me; or in the <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oISFeycGydQ">announcement trailer</a> when you leap from the shadow of Didi&#8217;s outstretched hand onto the looming shadow of a pistol.
This is beautiful symbolism: the role model being portrayed as both smaller than and
much larger than the lead really captures my imagination. It is also just a platform, and how many games have you played where the very platforms you jump
on, or the act of jupming itself, helps to drive the narrative? Contrast reminds me of the stories I was read
when I was a kid &#8211; like <a href="http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/620">Sylvie and Bruno</a>, <a href="http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/11">Alice in Wonderland</a>, and <a href="http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/225">At the Back of the North Wind</a> &#8211; and I hope to be able to put it
on my shelf along-side them.</p>

<p>Is that enough pressure?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meat's Edge]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/07/26/meats-edge/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-26T16:20:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/07/26/meats-edge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Meat&#8217;s Edge is a first person take on the unforgiving twitch platformer,
that doesn&#8217;t shy away from nausea and vomit. Missing a jump generally means
being torn into pink strips and recycled, rather than shimmying up a red pipe.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Meat&#8217;s Edge takes human reflexes to the extreme. It takes all the vomit
inducing vertigo of <a href="http://www.penny-arcade.com/comic/2008/11/03"> Mirror&#8217;s Edge </a> and just runs with it: camera angles are
spinning and flailing as your body rag-dolls madly after a failed landing.
More rolling, more cart-wheels, and more acrobatics. You spend the game
sprinting across rooftops, but unlike in Mirror&#8217;s Edge the rooftops of this
<a href="http://aliendovecote.com/uploads/twine/tycoon/crime.html">post neo-capitalist global empire</a> are designed to deter runners with the same
vicious geometry that modern architecture leverages against pigeons and the
homeless. I&#8217;m talking about spikes. This is is not a world that was designed
by the naive: they know what you are and what you do, and everything up here
is intended to stop you.</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='Everything about Meat&#8217;s Edge is designed to remind you what you&#8217;re made of.'>
In Mirror&#8217;s Edge the first person perspective was <a href="http://www.wired.com/gaming/gamingreviews/commentary/games/2008/11/gamesfrontiers_1117">emphasized</a> by including
heavy breathing, gasps, and your ever-present arms and legs. Meat&#8217;s Edge
takes this further: the phantom of your nose and upper lip is always
there; strands of your thick black hair fall into your face as the wind
crashing between the skyscrapers whips them to life; stand still for a moment
(not recommended) and you will notice tiny fibers <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Floater">floating around inside your eye</a>.
The environment is just as cruel as your anatomy: torrential
rain, tear gas, or smoke belched from the factories gets in your eyes, blurs
your vision, and reduces your chances of making that next jump; bright flashes
of light stay with you, discolouring your surroundings. Ice level? Yeah, Meat&#8217;s
Edge has <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/SlippySlideyIceWorld">an ice level</a>. Everything about Meat&#8217;s Edge is designed to remind you what you&#8217;re made of.
</span></p>

<p><span class='pullquote-left' data-pullquote='This is not a game that
EA would ever publish.'>
The level layouts are brutal! There are no brightly painted red pipes to shimmy up
in this game; there are no long runs through corridors. Meat&#8217;s Edge borrows
its level design from twitch platformers like <a href="http://supermeatboy.com/">Super Meat Boy</a>, and its pace (and
respect for your feelings) from <a href="http://superhexagon.com/"> Super Hexagon </a>. There are no arena zones filled with rifle toting corporate
military, and if you do happen to cross paths with an armed guard, renegade
cyborg, or corporate ninja charged with recovering the sensitive info you
are running&#8230; <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RwtifqCmGuw"> you do what we do </a>. Conflicts fought among the scaffolds and
reflective plexiglass tend to be short and conclusive. This is not a game that
EA would ever publish.</p>

<p>Oh, and the dude on your intercom? Calling you names the whole fucking way.
</span></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[10,000 Ninjas]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/07/26/ten-thousand-ninjas/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-26T14:29:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/07/26/ten-thousand-ninjas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In 10,000 Ninjas, you must combine insane twitch platforming, with patience,
focus and careful observation. Combine the precision and time constraints of
<a href="http://supermeatboy.com/"> Super Meat Boy </a> with the vexation of <a href="http://tenchu.wikia.com/wiki/Tenchu:_Stealth_Assassins">Tenchu</a> or <a href="http://www.markoftheninja.com/">Mark of the Ninja</a>,
and you&#8217;ve got 10,000 Ninjas.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Sometimes, when I&#8217;m sitting in a passport office on a warm day, or sipping
coldbrew on a courtyard patio, I&#8217;ll experience strange dreams. During
these times I find myself playing games that don&#8217;t yet, or may never,
exist. Mashing old games together, or stripping them apart&#8230; Digesting my
nostalgia? Today I played 10,000 Ninjas.</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='Take all the games on
lumosity, re-skin them for ninja stealth, and you&#8217;ve got 10,000 Ninjas!'>
Each level is an impossible gauntlet of spikes, drills, and samurai guards
making their rounds. In the shortest possible time, you must dodge, sneak, or
murder your way to the objectives without being seen (or at least without
being remembered). Death is frequent, and frustrating. Obstacles are mainly
static, but the guards&#8217; routes are procedurally generated so as to foil memory.
You can&#8217;t close your eyes and twitch your way through the levels,
you must pay attention to every tiny detail: there are loud cats, and squeaky
floor-boards; geisha entertaining guests behind paper thin walls; and an array
of low hanging branches and possibly scalable objects. Your peripheral vision is pushed to
its limits; likewise, your ability to multi-task. Take all the games on
<a href="http://www.lumosity.com/">lumosity</a>, re-skin them for ninja stealth, and you&#8217;ve got 10,000 Ninjas!
</span></p>

<p><span class='pullquote-left' data-pullquote='it will leave your spirit as drained as
your thumbs'>
Not only that! The levels in 10,000 Ninjas are not a single tauntingly difficult
path to a wailing damsel or hidden bandaid. Neither do they permit the open,
free-form, &#8216;do it your way&#8217; aesthetic of <a href="http://www.gog.com/gamecard/deus_ex">Deus Ex</a>, Tenchu, or Mark of the Ninja.
Each level is like three or four Super Meat Boy levels mashed into one, so that
the player must determine by trial and repeated, violent, <em>infuriating</em> failure
which of the many routes is actually viable. You might spend a half-hour crossing
the rooftops in the hopes that you are on the right track, only to realize that
finishing the level on time is impossible without entering the sewers! 10,000
Ninjas is maddeningly difficult, and it will leave your spirit as drained as
your thumbs.
</span></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Regex, Papers, Tower]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/07/22/regex/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-22T16:20:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/07/22/regex</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[RTP][apexgrows]{4,5} [CDP][leafsdrown]{5,8}</p>

<p>Regex Crossword
Tower Defense
Papers Please</p>

<p>Imagine a tower defense game in which the towers are regular expressions with
cooldown. You upgrade them by making them less specific, so that they can chip
away at the word enemies that roll ever closer.</p>

<p>Imagine a game in which you are a regular expression engine. A regex comes in,
and you have a limited number of clock cycles to understand it. Then inputs
start to pour in and you have to rapidly populate and return match data. Too
many mistakes and your library will gain a reputation as buggy; too slow and
folks will complain.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Echo Beasts]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/07/06/echo-beasts/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-06T17:13:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/07/06/echo-beasts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently became excited about the prospect of games for non-sighted people. This came after playing a couple of LD26 games that involved
elements of non-sighted play. These were <a href="http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-26/?action=preview&amp;uid=1158">Conversion</a>, and <a href="http://rac7.com/YouMustEscape/">You Must Escape</a>, and they succeed in being about accessibility without being accessible.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="center" src="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/images/you-must-escape.png" title="&#34;You Must Escape&#34;" alt="&#34;You Must Escape&#34;"></p>

<p><a href="http://rac7.com/YouMustEscape/">You Must Escape</a> was one of my favorite games of the LD26 (it was one of everyone&#8217;s favorites). It was moody, minimal, fun to control, and punishingly hard. The
game models navigation by echo-location, representing sound as point particles that emanate out from the source of the sound. This is really compelling!
Just moving around in the environment creates footsteps that are essentially explosions of little white particles, which bounce off the contours of the rooms
and hallways, giving you a sense of their shape. You can also press the spacebar to make an intentional sound, which is louder the longer you hold the spacebar, or
hold shift to creep, producing no sound. In addition to topography, you also get a sense of the &#8216;texture&#8217; of rooms, because the particles change colour depending
on the texture of the reflective surface. The textures presented in the game world are: grey for nothing, red for danger, and white for goal.</p>

<p>This by itself would be a fun game, but You Must Escape takes it further by introducing horrifying echo beasts: a source of sound that produces red particles, and
registers as danger. These creatures are mobile, and track toward the source of a sound. The later levels are extremely difficult, as you must often stay completely
still or navigate blindly by &#8220;creeping&#8221; around the level. In any case, the sound effects generated by echo beasts in motion are horrible alien noises, and the hero&#8217;s
death-rattle is so awful that I found myself dreading death (actually, I gave up in the end: this game is too scary for me).</p>

<p>Reading the comments to You Must Escape was neat: so many comments, but no-one commented on the inherent irony of the game. One comment in particular stood out
for me:</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;I&#8217;m so bad at these blind sound-dependent games. I wish I was better at them. Good job.&#8221;</p></blockquote>


<p>Since You Must Escape is not a sound-dependent game at all, I take &#8220;These blind sound-dependent games&#8221; to refer to games like <a href="http://rac7.com/YouMustEscape/">Conversion</a>, You Must Escape, and Traal
(in the most extreme case) in which elements of non-sighted play take the fore. They force the gamer to create a model of their environment in a way they might not be
used to, and I think this is a good thing. These elements are introduced in different levels of purity, or perhaps abstraction: in Conversion the game comes closest to
being an actual non-sighted experience; in You Must Escape the game models a non-sighted experience; and in Traal, where the player must close their eyes from time to
time in order to advance, we are just given a taste of non-sighted play.</p>

<p>Game designers are always systematizing elements of experience. Whether this is a physics engine, or a haunted forest, the designer chooses ways to evoke a particular
feeling in their players. I feel like You Must Escape does an excellent job of being a fun game about echolocation, but not such a great job of evoking the feeling of
echolocating.</p>

<p>has to choose
When I play a game like You Must Escape, which models something. , I always wonder about the choice of paint. For example: in an RPG amnesia is modeled by dropping a player
into an unfamiliar situation.
elements This phenomenon is one of degrees: in the case of Conversion, as I&#8217;ve mentioned, I am sad that the game remained inaccessible. This game, however, does not
present a non-sighted experience; it models one. The Why use point particles
to represent sound waves when sound waves would do a much better job?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.blindsidegame.com/">blindside</a>
<a href="http://www.papasangre.com/">papasangre</a>
<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zeBFCQ-aBds">nightjar</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elements of non-sighted play]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/06/25/elements-of-non-sighted-play/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-25T21:53:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/06/25/elements-of-non-sighted-play</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently became excited about the prospect of games for non-sighted people. This came after playing a couple of LD26 games that involved
elements of non-sighted play. These were <a href="http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-26/?action=preview&amp;uid=1158">Conversion</a>, and <a href="http://rac7.com/YouMustEscape/">You Must Escape</a>, and they succeed in being about accessibility without being accessible.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="center" src="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/images/conversion.png" title="&#34;Conversion&#34;" alt="&#34;Conversion&#34;"></p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='you should really
skip this bit and just play the damn game, that would be easier'>
<a href="http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-26/?action=preview&amp;uid=1158">Conversion</a> is a 1st (or possibly 3rd) person shooter that relies on none of the visual cues FPS players have been trained to use. The screen is black at all times,
except when messages concerning the state of the environment are displayed, these being &#8220;you bumped into a wall!&#8221; or &#8220;there is something soft and wet at your feet&#8221;.
The rest of the game information is conveyed with audio cues, such as a dripping noise, your own heartbeat, or a gunshot. These effects are presented using positional audio,
so that the player wearing headphones can effectively navigate to the source of a sound by positioning it directly in front of them and moving forward (you should really
skip this bit and just play the damn game, that would be easier).</p>

<p>Audio cues used in the game are gritty and emotional: water dripping in an empty room, a scratching noise, and a heartbeat are all very visceral. When I heard the gunshot
noise for the first time I literally leapt from my chair. After that I kept my tongue tucked behind my teeth in anticipation of more punishing audio to come. Conversion is
an excellent and effective game, and it was well received during LD26.
</span></p>

<p>The game introduces a sighted audience to elements of the world perceived by non-sighted people; its title is a reference to a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conversion_disorder"> kind of neurological disorder </a> that
can cause blindness.  That having been said, Conversion is not playable by non-sighted
gamers, and this feels like an ironic and tragic oversight. Despite <a href="https://twitter.com/spiridios">@spiridios</a>&#8217; claim that &#8220;You cannot see, so you must complete the game using only your sense of hearing
and sense of touch&#8221;, Conversion actually relies on the gamer&#8217;s sense of sight as well since it conveys certain spatial information in written messages. I want my review
to remain positive, because Conversion really is a great game, but I also can&#8217;t shy away from what I see as a glaring and embarrassing truth: a sighted gamer made a game
about being blind, without considering whether blind people would be able to play it too.</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='it is not interesting as a proof of concept'>
Conversion really does shine as an innovative indie title, but it is not interesting as a proof of concept. There are already fully 3D first-person-shooters made by and for non-sighted gamers. If you sit down and give them a
whirl as a sighted player&#8230; all I can say is that you will be stunned. Games like <a href="http://www.gmagames.com/sod.html"> Shades of Doom </a> and <a href="http://www.kaldobsky.com/audiogames/"> Swamp </a> are engineered to be complete, accessible FPS
experiences &#8211; an indie made for a game jam just can&#8217;t compete. I took some time to play SOD as part of writing this post: it was extremely
challenging for me to make any headway at all, but by all accounts this game broke ground. I haven&#8217;t tried Swamp, but <a href="http://soundplay.pitchfork.com/articles/shining-in-the-darkness/">Jason Johnson</a>&#8217;s review got me pretty excited. These
are the proof of concept games that could be considered landmarks in some way. Conversion is not them.
</span></p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='it was made to be experienced'>
Conversion is something that those games aren&#8217;t. I found the soundscape of Shades of Doom crowded and obnoxious. It was easy to navigate, with lots more
beeps and audio cues, but it wasn&#8217;t beautiful. SOD and Swamp are games that were made to be played.
Conversion, on the other hand, was tight and personal; it was made to be experienced. In particular it was made to be exprienced by a group of sighted gamers,
and to them it really was unique and new. This is well and good, but consider what was lost: Conversion could have been such
a perfect experience to share with non-sighted gamers, if only it didn&#8217;t rely on sight.
</span></p>

<p>There is a nice bridge to be built here, and the cost of construction is extremely low.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ravenous]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/06/24/ravenous/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-24T21:53:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/06/24/ravenous</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The creators of <a href="http://jonathanwhiting.com/ld/23/">Niña Nueve</a> (<a href="https://twitter.com/whitingjp">@whitingjp</a>) and <a href="http://www.newgrounds.com/portal/view/585599">These Robotic Hearts of Mine</a> (<a href="https://twitter.com/draknek">@Draknek</a>; an all time favorite of mine) comes <a href="http://jonathanwhiting.com/coding/traal/">Traal</a>, the
lovecraftian reverse stealth-em-up action puzzler for mobile and flash. Could we ask for anything more? A blindfold, perhaps?</p>

<!-- More -->


<p><img class="left-side" src="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/images/traal.jpg" title="&#34;Traal&#34;" alt="&#34;Traal&#34;"></p>

<p><a href="http://jonathanwhiting.com/coding/traal/">Traal</a> is an interesting reversal of the stealth game genre that takes place in a dungeon filled with spikes. The hero has a flashlight, and wherever she turns
the flashlight shines. If the flashlight lights up a monster, the hero freaks the fuck out and the player loses control of her for a moment. In a dungeon filled
with spikes, this momentary loss of control can mean death. Interestingly, the monsters (while deadly) rarely seem particularly interested in the hero, and ultimately
the enemy is her fear of the environment. Later in the game, she finds a blindfold and things get interesting. When the hero is wearing the blindfold, she can&#8217;t see
anything and the screen goes black. Now the player can still maneuver, and the monsters are still deadly, but the hero won&#8217;t freak out.</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='The blindfold introduces an element of non-sighted play'></p>

<p>The blindfold introduces an element of non-sighted play: the player now has the option of switching from sighted to non-sighted, and there are benefits to both.
In many rooms it is easy enough to memorize the layout and then feel your way through, but some rooms are too complicated for this to be effective.</p>

<p>The pace of this game is excellent, and it does an excellent job of wordlessly teaching the player how to play. I hope that one day that won&#8217;t bare saying,
but <a href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/09/22/osmos/">as we&#8217;ve seen</a>, even the most abstract games can mess this up. I especially love the feeling I get in Traal when walking into a trickier version of an early
lesson. I can almost hear the authors saying, &#8220;ok, but now the walls are spikes&#8221;.</p>

<p></span></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Two LD26 Entries]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/05/20/two-ld26-entries/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-20T18:09:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/05/20/two-ld26-entries</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-26/?action=preview&amp;uid=5275">DOE</a> and <a href="http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-26/?action=preview&amp;uid=2297">Bashland</a> are two LD26 games feel amazingly polished given that they were made in 48 hours. Bashland describes itself as a &#8220;Breakout Mario Mashup&#8221;, and does an incredible job of being just that. DOE takes place in a detailed and nuanced world, in which dreams can touch reality.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>DOE</h3>

<p><img class="left-side" src="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/images/we-can-all-dream.png" title="&#34;we can all dream&#34;" alt="&#34;we can all dream&#34;"></p>

<p>One of the clever decisions in DOE is to have the game set in a detailed and nuanced world, without ever really referencing that world. In the author&#8217;s own words, &#8220;The whole universe that I imagined is in the end much bigger than what is exposed in the game.&#8221; DOE&#8217;s gameplay is familiar &#8211; it is a mixture of pushing blocks and avoiding guards &#8211; but the visual elements, events, and ending give us a sense that we are experiencing the exposed edge of something bigger.</p>

<p>In the early areas you explore by pushing walls away, presumably with your mind, though there is also evidence to suggest that your mind powers are being suppressed somehow (thus, we may suspect that someone is helping you escape). Early on we get some clues by way of overheard conversation, or intrapersonal communication:</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;Let them imagine you&#8217;re dead, and you will be.&#8221;</p></blockquote>




<blockquote><p>&#8220;This is going to be tricky&#8230; and I can&#8217;t dream!&#8221;</p></blockquote>


<p>When the game ends, all I want it more. How do you make a game like this in 48 hours?</p>

<h3>Bashland</h3>

<p>Bashland, on the other hand, is not a subtly, nuanced or carefully constructed poem fit tightly in a 48 hour shell; it is a full blown explosion where nostalgia slams up against honestly amazing assets. When I started it, I had to double check that I was not, in fact, playing a jam game. The music, graphics, and gameplay are completely stunning and 100% communicate the subject. The music! It is just baddass.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/images/bashland.png" title="&#34;A Breakout Mario Mashup&#34;" alt="&#34;A Breakout Mario Mashup&#34;"></p>

<blockquote><p>BASHLAND. When you played breakout, this is what you imagined you were playing. Nice slow reveal. @McFunkypants http://t.co/Cetc19ApVW #LD48</p><footer><strong>@ArrogantGamer</strong> <cite>A Truly Arrogant Man</cite></footer></blockquote>


<p>When I tweeted this, I actually hadn&#8217;t read the author&#8217;s statement quoted above. The game feels like Breakout literally breaking out of the restrictive old-school arcade genre &#8211; it&#8217;s as though the little ball finally bashed through its enclosure and into someone else&#8217;s game. Gradually, we realize this is exactly what happened. It is so satisfying to bash your way through the old Mario stages, and the control is also really nice and smooth. Finally, if you manage to bash away too much of the level you can no longer win: so practice some restraint!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minimalism: Pyramid]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/05/15/minimalism-pyramid/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-15T23:37:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/05/15/minimalism-pyramid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Many LD26 games chose to incorporate the theme of Minimalism by being visually simple. Pyramid was visually simple as a consequence of being minimalist. Burgess chose to strip away the unnecessary elements of a rogue-like, and left us with a stunning piece of work. I will dwell on the degree to which Burgess hit the theme.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="left-side" src="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/images/pyramid.png"></p>

<p>Minimalism presents something similar to prototype. I think that word has a bit of baggage: evoking an incomplete or fragile &#8216;first try&#8217; that is a basis for greater efforts. Prototypes aren&#8217;t just a quick slap job, they must also be the minimal viable product. That&#8217;s why projects start as prototypes, but it is not to say that we can&#8217;t also start with something bigger and then shave it down to a prototype. This is how I understood the LD26 theme, and I think that Burgess really expressed it well in Pyramid.</p>

<p><img class="left-side" src="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/images/hooked-lash.png">
<img class="right-side" src="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/images/one-of-the-corrupted.png"></p>

<p>Pyramid&#8217;s levels are squares of randomly generated passages; the hero&#8217;s vision is limited, so when the levels start to get really big it starts to feel really murky. If Pyramid&#8217;s levels didn&#8217;t grow, we wouldn&#8217;t understand the name. If Pyramid were called another name, we wouldn&#8217;t understand why the levels grow. Remove either element and what remains doesn&#8217;t make sense. Very little is embellished in Pyramid; there is very little excess. That&#8217;s not to say there isn&#8217;t anything left that could still be stripped away: burgess named things. Numbers appear on the screen to indicate the damage the hero deals or takes: this is enough to express the gradual powering up of the hero. Burgess, however, chose to name the different power levels. For example, in Pyramid &#8220;10&#8221; is called &#8220;Imperious Axe of Truth&#8221;. The monsters are also named.</p>

<p>In terms of how the game plays: it is smooth and fun. The game teaches us all the necessary mechanics in the first 3 levels, and then just gets tougher and tougher. The only thing that is left to us to discover is how combat works. I found out around level 12 that if you touch an enemy you attack it. That&#8217;s not all though: unlike a run-of-the-mill rogue-like, it is possible to dance with enemies and outwit them. For me this is great: the game is not just a resource management slog, it involves patience and wit as well.</p>

<p>The game goes on forever, but I&#8217;ve been assured that level 48 is the last time any new content is introduced.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vision by Proxy]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/04/06/vision-by-proxy/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-06T21:49:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/04/06/vision-by-proxy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In Vision by Proxy, you are a nearly blind extraterrestrial who sees by
stealing human eyes. When you steal a pair of eyes, looking out through them
gives you a different perspective on the world. A child&#8217;s world is full
of magic, while an engineer sees the hidden uses of things. To progress
through the game, you must collect eyes.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="left-side" src="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/images/vision-by-proxy.png"></p>

<p>Your alien character does not power up by collecting eyes. Instead you gradually
gain access to different interpretations of the level&#8217;s layout. Thus, ideally,
the game is about remembering that you can more easily climb the little girl&#8217;s
play-fort then the anime chick&#8217;s Japanese temple. Some perspectives give you access
to the insides of things, or to a variety of floating platforms.</p>

<p>This game has evolved quite a bit since its initial incarnation, and some of my
complaints have been addressed. In the original game there were only four eyes to
collect, but in the more recent &#8220;Ms Vision by Proxy&#8221; (a sequel) we are introduced
to seven or so. This is good. When we enter a level we aren&#8217;t certain what eyes
will be available, and only after developing a vocabulary of game objects we can begin
to predict what eyes we need in order to progress.</p>

<p>That being said, it suffers from the levels being too big for the hero: the gameplay
is a little like a metroidvania, but the RPG elements are not played up enough for trekking back and forth across
the level to really be exciting. In addition, the puzzles are not really difficult or
focused and solving them ends up feeling inevitable. This game needs an overworld map, or teleportation, or something
to make the player feel like they are gathering information towards eventually solving
the puzzle, rather than just walking back and forth.</p>

<p>In an earlier post I proposed a game about mediums. I think merging the theme of
Death-Death-Evolution and the mechanics of Vision by Proxy would be cool. Imagine with me:</p>

<blockquote class='imagine-with-me'><p>You play as a group of characters positioned all around a level, separated by time and space (that is, no two characters exist at the same time). There is no central alien collector, instead you can switch between the characters and each can explore a small part of the level. Sometimes the levels laid out differently in different times, much like the way different eyes affect the level layouts in VBP. Some of the characters are fenced in by an obstacle that they can&#8217;t overcome, but that another character could.</p><p>This solves the problem of the level size &#8211; the player can now take in all (or most) the of the terrain features at once, right at the start of the level.  Now we add the DDE element: in order to advance, the player moves the free characters into areas their abilities allow them to reach, and then suicides them in some manner provided by the level. When the player flips to the other characters, there is now a ghost haunting the site of the death. Since the characters are mediums, they are able to tap into these spirits and gain the abilities that they need to move through the level. Gradually, and with much planning, the remaining characters move about the level collecting and combining spirits until they are able to reach the goal (whatever that happens to be).</p></blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Three Body Problem]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/12/14/the-three-body-problem/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-14T11:21:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/12/14/the-three-body-problem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Death Death Evolution]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/10/01/death-death-evolution/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-01T19:35:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/10/01/death-death-evolution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In Death Death Evolution, there is no escape. You must die to advance.
This game proposes a new relationship between the platform
jumper and the pits. In later stages I was actively looking for places
where I could die in a particular way, in order to unlock the tools I
might need later. There are even levels where you can die in irrelevant
ways, if you choose to, so that if you want to you can be stingy with death,
or feed her to bursting in order to fully &#8216;power up&#8217;.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="right-side" src="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/images/dde.png"></p>

<p>Nice game: I want more. More different animals, evolution abilities that
make more sense (I mean&#8230; I fell on spikes and could subsequently break
balloons with my head). I think we could take the mechanic of dying
for personal gain, switch up the theme a bit, and make a truly golden game
about ghosts or reincarnation or something.</p>

<blockquote class='imagine-with-me'><p>Let the player control people who are in touch with the spirit world. Mediums.<br/>You lead them about, and when they come in contact with a ghost they take on<br/>some aspect of that ghost&#8217;s former life. At first, there are not ghosts and only<br/>a collection of living mediums. The player strategically kills off her mediums,<br/>forcing them to haunt the place of their death but also allowing later mediums to<br/>proceed further through the game. Perhaps there is an economy of souls, such that<br/>a player must be careful who is killed when.</p></blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Patience and Regret]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/09/29/patience-and-regret/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-29T12:49:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/09/29/patience-and-regret</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are three &#8216;zones&#8217;, collections of levels each of which give you a different flavor of game play. The
ambient &#8216;vanilla&#8217; levels build on the theme of &#8216;become the biggest&#8217;. The other two zones change game play
by introducing new elements: artificial lifeforms for you to compete with; and force attractors that act
as a center of gravity. I still haven&#8217;t figured out how to beat the force attractor levels, but the ambient
and survival levels are great! Beating three ai motes at once is tricky, and took me several tries.</p>

<p>Osmos contains one of my favorite underused mechanics: patience. I can
understand why this mechanic doesn&#8217;t get a lot of use. In Braid it was
presented only to the most hardcore, and in SS&amp;S EP it was an opt-in
system. In both cases, you didn&#8217;t have to play the waiting game if you
didn&#8217;t want to&#8230; but in Osmos you better get used to it. In the force
attractor levels you are in orbit around a central goo ball, and you
want to be the biggest. Playing these levels I felt like I had close
to zero agency. &#8220;Hey man still in orbit around the force attractor?&#8221;
&#8220;yeah, how bout you?&#8221; &#8220;yup. OK well, see you next time around.&#8221; With
each tearfully slow revolution you might pick up a tiny bit of mass,
and in this manner you grow. Admittedly, Osmos does give you the option
of speeding up time, which I discovered late in the levels by accident
(I don&#8217;t pay much attention to written instructions); even on fast
forward you still end up spinning in circles for an eternity before
you finally have enough mass to just leave and make a sandwich while
you become the biggest. Great game! But listen, that&#8217;s not all it takes.</p>

<p>In addition to patience, the game rewards the &#8216;letting go&#8217;. I guess it
is a very eastern-religion game in some sense: if you are aiming at
a particular goo ball, and in your clumsy sputtering you manage to
miss the mark, then you had better just let go. You could come to a full
stop and reverse your momentum, or try to come around for a second pass,
but in doing so you lose more than you probably will gain. The best
thing to do when you lose something (like in real life) is to adjust your
plan.</p>

<p>Patience: become the biggest, and never look back.</p>

<p>of which introduces a new element: opponents that behave
in one way or another; force attractors around which all the motes orbit;</p>

<p>The next few give us toy examples of the game&#8217;s &#8216;zones&#8217;, each of which tests us by introducing new elements.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Become the Biggest]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/09/22/osmos/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-22T18:28:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/09/22/osmos</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You could play Osmos with no more instruction: the imperative to grow will guide you naturally
and inexorably. Despite its simplicity, Osmos does insist on spelling everything out in tutorial levels. I
really enjoy early learning stages in games, especially the ones that teach you about the world, rather than
the control scheme. I&#8217;m usually not pleased when English language words appear on the screen telling me
to tap X rapidly or whatnot. Unless the appearance of language is consistent with the theme of the game,
(like in Analogue, for example) this can be a real turn off. I&#8217;m going to go into some detail about the tutorial
levels (there are two) because I think Osmos is an excellent example of how easily a great beginning can
turn foul.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Starting a game with a quote by a physicist or philosopher is a great idea: it sets the stage, and fills my mind
with well grounded ideas. No better way to quickly build a framework in which a player&#8217;s understanding
of the theme and action can grow, than by analogy. Osmos begins with a quote by Newton that has acquired
great cultural weight, and has as much meaning in ethics as it does in physics. Great first moment.</p>

<p>Then, fade in to a beautiful blue orb, pulsing and swimming with activity. What is this? Is this the universe? Is this
life itself, or God? No, the game corrects us: &#8220;This is you&#8221;. Beautiful! OK! Now I know what kind of game
this is and who I am, just give me a goal and I&#8217;m off!</p>

<p><img class="left-side" src="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/images/this-is-you.png"></p>

<p>Aiming for the home run, Osmos zooms out, and shows us what we need to do: &#8220;Propel yourself to the blue
circle and come to a stop&#8221;. For me, a smooth introduction like this is the sweetest thing. I rarely
play games to their conclusion, and I judge very quickly. Ambient music, soft blue colour-scheme, and
simple direct instructions are exactly everything that I need. So, having been told what I am and
where to go, naturally I start clicking.</p>

<p>Nothing&#8230; click, click, click! Wait what? But I thought every action had an equal and opposite reaction?
Shouldn&#8217;t something happen when I click? Oh wait&#8230; I see what&#8217;s up. Osmos doesn&#8217;t care if I understand what
I am and where I should go: it is too humble (or something) to anticipate that I could have understood by now
just based on the theme and visuals. So, reluctantly, I press the spacebar one more time.</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;Hey, listen! You navigate by aligning the cursor behind you and pressing the left mouse button&#8221;</p></blockquote>


<p>Arglebargle!!! I love Osmos: great game. I&#8217;m just so, so, so disappointed when that little sprite
shows up in every game I play to remind me of what I already know. I&#8217;ve never read a novel or watched a
film that presumed the need to explain the medium: yet every second video game does this. Especially
considering that Osmos was released for a platform with exactly one button &#8211; your finger &#8211; which can only
be used to &#8216;tip-tap&#8217;&#8230; it is very sad that I&#8217;m not allowed to play until that vile spectre has made my
means of agency explicit.</p>

<p>The rest of the instructions &#8211; that is, to absorb small motes and avoid big ones &#8211; are also unnecessary
in the post katamari damaci world. Especially when the reds of warning are so vivid, and the peaceful blues
so soft and attractive. Nothing in the world could be more evident, once you have understood that &#8216;this is you&#8217;. If
that&#8217;s me, and that big red ball isn&#8217;t me, then there is no way I&#8217;m going anywhere near it. I&#8217;ll go chill
with these little blue balls I can shove around. Oh shit I got bigger! Ha, and the red ball changed color! Time
to win!</p>

<p>See: no need to instruct. Hey! Are you listening?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Post]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/09/17/first-post/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-17T18:58:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/09/17/first-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Whoa!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
