<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: LD48 | Arrogant Gamer]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/categories/ld48/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-20T23:27:31-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Arrogant Gamer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Misdirection & Dreams]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2014/05/02/beneath-the-surface/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-02T18:25:30-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2014/05/02/beneath-the-surface</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&ldquo;Beneath the Surface&rdquo; was a great theme. If you made a game that said, <em>this
is a game that seems to be one thing, but beneath the surface it is another.&ldquo;</em>,
then you have my love. So far, <a href="https://twitter.com/jezzamonn">@jezzamonn</a>&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-29/?action=preview&amp;uid=10217">Generic Adventure Game</a> is the
game that nailed that one the best.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The game starts with a beautiful misdirection, playing on the investment of
player into avatar. For the first moments of the game you play a generic hero
who can press &lsquo;A&rsquo; to kill an adorable slime for XP. The slime is the player,
but the player won&rsquo;t understand this right away.</p>

<p>Misdirection stands in a clique at the heart of game design, facing inwards and
passing around a pipe. Unlike the rest of the elements of play you might encounter
in a game, a misdirection can be experience meaningfully exactly once by each player.
It is a narrative technique, but it is one that is expressed purely in the meta
world of interface. There is no dialog or plot twist: we are set up to expect one
thing, and then we press an arrow key and the wrong thing happens. Simple, but
so, so effective.</p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<p>Now, confused and unsure of what to <em>do</em> in the game, we are left alone to be a helpless
slime for a while. Amnesia and helplessness are go-toes of the game-to-brain API. The
player does not, by default, know what has happened in the moments leading up to the game
or what the game&rsquo;s objective are. Allowing the player to stew in this uncertainty is
always great, and many of the classic JRPG characters we know and love made it into
our brains this way.</p>

<p>Eventually the game explains: hold shift to dream.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/slime-dream.png" title="&ldquo;Slime is Dreaming&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>As long as you hold shift, you are playing a different game: you jump higher and
move faster, there are no heroes to kill you and the landscape is lush,
verdant, soft, and anti-aliased. You can hop around and explore, and the game
generally just feels <em>better</em>. Meanwhile, on the surface, you are dying repeatedly.</p>

<p>For me, this is a <em>new trick</em>: a game that sucks, in which you can hold shift to play a fun
game. What a totally rad idea! I can&rsquo;t help by imagine all the places a game could go from
there: perhaps the slime unlocks deep and ancient secrets, or saves the world
(perhaps the player sometimes forgets they are holding shift and that this is a dream); perhaps there
are gates in the dream world that lead out to the aether beyond worlds, and
the slime loses its connection to its body, only then learning to appreciate what it lost;
perhaps the slime meets a spiritual guide that teaches it to bring its dream
self into the real world. Perhaps!</p>

<p>When your game starts with such brilliant underpinnings,
where you take it is of little consequence. Generic Adventure Game does not
disappoint.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
