<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Mark of the Ninja | Arrogant Gamer]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/categories/mark-of-the-ninja/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-02T22:05:59+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Arrogant Gamer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[10,000 Ninjas]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/07/26/ten-thousand-ninjas/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-26T14:29:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/07/26/ten-thousand-ninjas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In 10,000 Ninjas, you must combine insane twitch platforming, with patience,
focus and careful observation. Combine the precision and time constraints of
<a href="http://supermeatboy.com/"> Super Meat Boy </a> with the vexation of <a href="http://tenchu.wikia.com/wiki/Tenchu:_Stealth_Assassins">Tenchu</a> or <a href="http://www.markoftheninja.com/">Mark of the Ninja</a>,
and you've got 10,000 Ninjas.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Sometimes, when I'm sitting in a passport office on a warm day, or sipping
coldbrew on a courtyard patio, I'll experience strange dreams. During
these times I find myself playing games that don't yet, or may never,
exist. Mashing old games together, or stripping them apart... Digesting my
nostalgia? Today I played 10,000 Ninjas.</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='Take all the games on
<a href="http://www.lumosity.com/">lumosity</a>, re-skin them for ninja stealth, and you&#8217;ve got 10,000 Ninjas!'>
Each level is an impossible gauntlet of spikes, drills, and samurai guards
making their rounds. In the shortest possible time, you must dodge, sneak, or
murder your way to the objectives without being seen (or at least without
being remembered). Death is frequent, and frustrating. Obstacles are mainly
static, but the guards' routes are procedurally generated so as to foil memory.
You can't close your eyes and twitch your way through the levels,
you must pay attention to every tiny detail: there are loud cats, and squeaky
floor-boards; geisha entertaining guests behind paper thin walls; and an array
of low hanging branches and possibly scalable objects. Your peripheral vision is pushed to
its limits; likewise, your ability to multi-task. Take all the games on
<a href="http://www.lumosity.com/">lumosity</a>, re-skin them for ninja stealth, and you've got 10,000 Ninjas!
</span></p>

<p><span class='pullquote-left' data-pullquote='it will leave your spirit as drained as
your thumbs'>
Not only that! The levels in 10,000 Ninjas are not a single tauntingly difficult
path to a wailing damsel or hidden bandaid. Neither do they permit the open,
free-form, 'do it your way' aesthetic of <a href="http://www.gog.com/gamecard/deus_ex">Deus Ex</a>, Tenchu, or Mark of the Ninja.
Each level is like three or four Super Meat Boy levels mashed into one, so that
the player must determine by trial and repeated, violent, <em>infuriating</em> failure
which of the many routes is actually viable. You might spend a half-hour crossing
the rooftops in the hopes that you are on the right track, only to realize that
finishing the level on time is impossible without entering the sewers! 10,000
Ninjas is maddeningly difficult, and it will leave your spirit as drained as
your thumbs.
</span></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
