<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Conversion | Arrogant Gamer]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/categories/conversion/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-28T22:16:00-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Arrogant Gamer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elements of non-sighted play]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/06/25/elements-of-non-sighted-play/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-25T21:53:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/06/25/elements-of-non-sighted-play</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently became excited about the prospect of games for non-sighted people. This came after playing a couple of LD26 games that involved
elements of non-sighted play. These were <a href="http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-26/?action=preview&amp;uid=1158">Conversion</a>, and <a href="http://rac7.com/YouMustEscape/">You Must Escape</a>, and they succeed in being about accessibility without being accessible.</p>

<p>I wrote about You Must Escape as <a href="/blog/2013/07/06/echo-beasts/">a separate post</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="center" src="/images/conversion.png" title="&ldquo;Conversion&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<p>The game introduces a sighted audience to elements of the world perceived by non-sighted people; its title is a reference to a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conversion_disorder">kind of neurological disorder</a> that
can cause blindness.  That having been said, Conversion is not playable by non-sighted
gamers, and this feels like an ironic and tragic oversight. Despite <a href="https://twitter.com/spiridios">@spiridios</a>&lsquo; claim that &ldquo;You cannot see, so you must complete the game using only your sense of hearing
and sense of touch&rdquo;, Conversion actually relies on the gamer&rsquo;s sense of sight as well since it conveys certain spatial information in written messages. I want my review
to remain positive, because Conversion really is a great game, but I also can&rsquo;t shy away from what I see as a glaring and embarrassing truth: a sighted gamer made a game
about being blind, without considering whether blind people would be able to play it too.</p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<p>There is a nice bridge to be built here, and the cost of construction is extremely low.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
