<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ludum&nbsp;Dare | Arrogant Gamer]]></title>
  <link href="http://arrogantgamer.com/blog/categories/ludum-nbsp-dare/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://arrogantgamer.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-13T17:24:37-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://arrogantgamer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Arrogant Gamer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Death Death Evolution]]></title>
    <link href="http://arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/10/01/death-death-evolution/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-01T19:35:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/10/01/death-death-evolution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Interesting learning experience! I had it spoiled a little by reading
a review (like this one) ahead of time, but basically the game does a
good job of teaching you how to play. I have an interesting complaint
that, admittedly, is forming in my mind as I write this. In a lot of
platformers, you die and that teaches you what not to do... and if the
deaths are really inevitable (like some of the ones in Limbo), that
kind of pisses me off. For example, in Limbo there is a bit with crushers
that is exactly designed so that no matter how clever you are you won't
make it through on your first try (well... maybe someone out there
is this clever). That pisses me off because I like the feeling that I
have all the pieces of the puzzle laid out before me, so that with
patience and wisdom I will be able to out-smart death.</p>

<p>In Death Death Evolution, there is no escape. You must die to advance.
Am I upset by this? No, after some thought I realize that I am instead
pleased: this game proposes a new relationship between the platform
jumper and the pits. In later stages I was actively looking for places
where I could die in a particular way, in order to unlock the tools I
might need later. There are even levels where you can die in irrelevant
ways, if you choose to, so that if you want to you can be stingy with death,
or feed her to bursting in order to fully 'power up'.</p>

<p>Nice game: I want more. More different animals, evolution abilities that
make more sense (I mean... I fell on spikes and could subsequently break
balloons with my head). Maybe someone could take the mechanic of dying
for personal gain, switch up the theme a bit, and make a truely golden game
about ghosts or demons or something.</p>

<p>This is the only game I've played from Ludum Dare 24. I like the theme of
Evolution (as a child, EVO was one of my favourite games), so I imagine
there are others that I should probably check out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
