<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: imagine | Arrogant Gamer]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/categories/imagine/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-27T22:23:21+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Arrogant Gamer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Regex, Papers, Tower]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/07/22/regex/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-22T16:20:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/07/22/regex</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[RTP][apexgrows]{4,5} [CDP][leafsdrown]{5,8}</p>

<p>Regex Crossword
Tower Defense
Papers Please</p>

<p>Imagine a tower defense game in which the towers are regular expressions with
cooldown. You upgrade them by making them less specific, so that they can chip
away at the word enemies that roll ever closer.</p>

<p>Imagine a game in which you are a regular expression engine. A regex comes in,
and you have a limited number of clock cycles to understand it. Then inputs
start to pour in and you have to rapidly populate and return match data. Too
many mistakes and your library will gain a reputation as buggy; too slow and
folks will complain.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vision by Proxy]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/04/06/vision-by-proxy/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-06T21:49:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2013/04/06/vision-by-proxy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In Vision by Proxy, you are a nearly blind extraterrestrial who sees by
stealing human eyes. When you steal a pair of eyes, looking out through them
gives you a different perspective on the world. A child's world is full
of magic, while an engineer sees the hidden uses of things. To progress
through the game, you must collect eyes.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="left-side" src="/images/vision-by-proxy.png"></p>

<p>Your alien character does not power up by collecting eyes. Instead you gradually
gain access to different interpretations of the level's layout. Thus, ideally,
the game is about remembering that you can more easily climb the little girl's
play-fort then the anime chick's Japanese temple. Some perspectives give you access
to the insides of things, or to a variety of floating platforms.</p>

<p>This game has evolved quite a bit since its initial incarnation, and some of my
complaints have been addressed. In the original game there were only four eyes to
collect, but in the more recent "Ms Vision by Proxy" (a sequel) we are introduced
to seven or so. This is good. When we enter a level we aren't certain what eyes
will be available, and only after developing a vocabulary of game objects we can begin
to predict what eyes we need in order to progress.</p>

<p>That being said, it suffers from the levels being too big for the hero: the gameplay
is a little like a metroidvania, but the RPG elements are not played up enough for trekking back and forth across
the level to really be exciting. In addition, the puzzles are not really difficult or
focused and solving them ends up feeling inevitable. This game needs an overworld map, or teleportation, or something
to make the player feel like they are gathering information towards eventually solving
the puzzle, rather than just walking back and forth.</p>

<p>In an earlier post I proposed a game about mediums. I think merging the theme of
Death-Death-Evolution and the mechanics of Vision by Proxy would be cool. Imagine with me:</p>

<p><blockquote class='imagine-with-me'><p>You play as a group of characters positioned all around a level, separated by time and space (that is, no two characters exist at the same time). There is no central alien collector, instead you can switch between the characters and each can explore a small part of the level. Sometimes the levels laid out differently in different times, much like the way different eyes affect the level layouts in VBP. Some of the characters are fenced in by an obstacle that they can't overcome, but that another character could.</p></p><p><p>This solves the problem of the level size -- the player can now take in all (or most) the of the terrain features at once, right at the start of the level.  Now we add the DDE element: in order to advance, the player moves the free characters into areas their abilities allow them to reach, and then suicides them in some manner provided by the level. When the player flips to the other characters, there is now a ghost haunting the site of the death. Since the characters are mediums, they are able to tap into these spirits and gain the abilities that they need to move through the level. Gradually, and with much planning, the remaining characters move about the level collecting and combining spirits until they are able to reach the goal (whatever that happens to be).</p></blockquote></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Death Death Evolution]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/10/01/death-death-evolution/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-01T19:35:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.arrogantgamer.com/blog/2012/10/01/death-death-evolution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In Death Death Evolution, there is no escape. You must die to advance.
This game proposes a new relationship between the platform
jumper and the pits. In later stages I was actively looking for places
where I could die in a particular way, in order to unlock the tools I
might need later. There are even levels where you can die in irrelevant
ways, if you choose to, so that if you want to you can be stingy with death,
or feed her to bursting in order to fully 'power up'.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="right-side" src="/images/dde.png"></p>

<p>Nice game: I want more. More different animals, evolution abilities that
make more sense (I mean... I fell on spikes and could subsequently break
balloons with my head). I think we could take the mechanic of dying
for personal gain, switch up the theme a bit, and make a truly golden game
about ghosts or reincarnation or something.</p>

<p><blockquote class='imagine-with-me'><p>Let the player control people who are in touch with the spirit world. Mediums.<br/>You lead them about, and when they come in contact with a ghost they take on<br/>some aspect of that ghost's former life. At first, there are not ghosts and only<br/>a collection of living mediums. The player strategically kills off her mediums,<br/>forcing them to haunt the place of their death but also allowing later mediums to<br/>proceed further through the game. Perhaps there is an economy of souls, such that<br/>a player must be careful who is killed when.</p></blockquote></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
